<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="https://tuckerm.us/">
  <title>Tucker McKnight's blog</title>
  <link href="https://tuckerm.us/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://tuckerm.us/"/>
  <updated>2023-07-22T07:16:15Z</updated>
  <id>https://tuckerm.us/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Tucker McKnight</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Link List: Social Media &amp; Our Attention Spans</title>
    <link href="https://tuckerm.us/posts/social-media-distraction-links/"/>
    <updated>2023-07-22T07:16:15Z</updated>
    <id>https://tuckerm.us/posts/social-media-distraction-links/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some articles related to social media and how it may affect our brains.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Using Obsidian as an Org-Mode Replacement</title>
    <link href="https://tuckerm.us/posts/using-osbidian-as-an-org-mode-replacement/"/>
    <updated>2023-05-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://tuckerm.us/posts/using-osbidian-as-an-org-mode-replacement/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was an Emacs user for several years before switching to Neovim, and then recently switched to Kakoune. I&#39;ve been getting more serious about using the note-taking app &lt;a href=&quot;https://obsidian.md/&quot;&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt; as an editor-agnostic replacement for org-mode, and so far it has filled that role nicely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan on writing a series of blog posts about how I&#39;m recreating my org-mode usage in Obsidian. Some of the things I used org-mode for are not really possible in Obsidian right now, so writing some plugins might be part of this work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;recreating-org-mode&#39;s-agenda-view&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Recreating Org-mode&#39;s Agenda View&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite features in org-mode was the agenda view. There are two community-made plugins for Obsidian that allow you to create an agenda view: Tasks and Dataview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s say we have this list of tasks somewhere in our Obsidian vault:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;- [ ] Dentist appointment [due:: 2023-05-22]
- [ ] Sweep the kitchen floor [due:: 2023-05-23]
- [ ] Do laundry [due:: 2023-05-23]
- [ ] Make post about Obsidian [due:: 2023-05-23]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordinarily, the &lt;code&gt;[due:: 2023-05-23]&lt;/code&gt; syntax is meaningless to Obsidian. However, both Tasks and Dataview know how to parse that format and use it for displaying lists of tasks elsewhere in your notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;tasks-plugin&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Tasks Plugin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tasks is the more simple option here. Dataview allows you to add custom values to your notes that you can query for later; if that sounds unnecessary to you, go with Tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once your tasks are labeled with due dates, in a fence (that&#39;s what those three backtick characters are called) labeled &amp;quot;tasks&amp;quot;, you can tell it to show you your upcoming tasks, sorted by day of the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can display an agenda view like org-mode by putting this in a note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;```tasks
not done
due before next week
group by due
```
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you preview that note, Obsidian will replace the &lt;code&gt; ```tasks&lt;/code&gt; block with this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2023-05-22 Monday&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dentist appointment 📅 2023-05-22&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2023-05-23 Tuesday&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sweep the kitchen floor 📅 2023-05-23&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do laundry 📅 2023-05-23&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make post about Obsidian 📅 2023-05-23&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Viola -- there is your agenda view. I like to have a &amp;quot;home note&amp;quot; that serves as a kind of dashboard, and I have that agenda view code block in it. But you can use more filters to get an agenda view for a specific project -- see &lt;a href=&quot;https://publish.obsidian.md/tasks/Queries/Filters&quot;&gt;the plugin&#39;s documentation&lt;/a&gt; to get an idea of what you can do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;dataview-plugin&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Dataview Plugin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dataview comes highly recommended by Obsidian power users. If you simply want an agenda view for your tasks, it&#39;s overkill. But if you&#39;re trying to replace Emacs, it&#39;s exactly-the-right-amount-of-kill. To stay focused, I&#39;ll only show how to create a basic agenda view here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same syntax for defining due dates works with Dataview, so our task list looks the same as before. The agenda view query is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;```dataview
TASK
WHERE due
AND due - date(today) &amp;lt; dur(7days)
GROUP BY due
```
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The syntax is not as English-like as with the Tasks plugin, but in return you can use Dataview for more types of queries beyond just task items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-just-wish-it-worked-outside-of-obsidian&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;I Just Wish It Worked Outside of Obsidian&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest thing I miss about using Emacs is that just about everything you do
can be done inside of Emacs. Sharing the same UI, the same shortcuts, the same everything
for both coding and taking notes is fantastic. While I can edit my Obsidian notes
in my new text editor of choice (Kakoune), there are still plenty of features that only
work within Obsidian itself. These agenda view examples are such features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a sense, this isn&#39;t much different from org-mode, which requires you to use Emacs. Both
Emacs and Obsidian offer an agenda view, and to see them, you must be using those respective
applications. But the fact that Emacs was &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; the same application I used to edit code
made it much more convenient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, both of the plugins I mentioned here rely on features that are specific to Obsidian;
they can&#39;t be run outside of it. Some kind of command-line tool that can query markdown files like
Dataview would be a real holy grail for editor-agnostic, text-based task management.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I Like Mastodon (for non-techies)</title>
    <link href="https://tuckerm.us/posts/why-i-like-mastodon/"/>
    <updated>2023-05-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://tuckerm.us/posts/why-i-like-mastodon/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 30th, 2023 update:&lt;/strong&gt; A show on NPR today aired an episode about our attention spans and how they
can be affected be social media. You can give it a listen here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://the1a.org/segments/how-much-are-we-paying-attention-really-2/&quot;&gt;https://the1a.org/segments/how-much-are-we-paying-attention-really-2/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was never a big Twitter user, but after some recent decisions from the management
(like unbanning a bunch of actual neo nazis), I decided to start
using Mastodon. But the thing that excites me most about Mastodon is not Mastodon
itself: it&#39;s what Mastodon represents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the surface, Mastodon looks like a 1-for-1 clone of Twitter. Users can post short
messages, attach photos or videos, and make replies to other posts. You choose who
you want to follow, and Mastodon shows you their posts in chronological order. And right there
we already see our first difference: Twitter (and Facebook, and all the others)
will show you content &amp;quot;related&amp;quot; to people you follow so that you always have more posts
to see. You can always keep scrolling; you can always keep watching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mastodon, on the other hand, doesn&#39;t do that. As you scroll through your Mastodon feed,
eventually you will see the last post you read the day before, and that means &lt;em&gt;you&#39;re done.&lt;/em&gt;
You did it. You read all of the social media posts you signed up to see that day; you can move
on. Mastodon isn&#39;t going to find more posts so that you can keep scrolling. Why is that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike most other social media sites, Mastodon is not run by a profit-driven company. The code
is written by a nonprofit with help from hundreds of volunteers around the world,
and the servers that store your data are run by additional volunteers who collect donations to
keep their systems running. This means, unlike for-profit social media, Mastodon does not
have the incentive to keep your eyes glued to your phone for as long as possible. For Twitter,
the longer you look at the screen, the more ads you will see. Twitter, Facebook, YouTube, TikTok,
and all other profit-driven social media sites spend a ton of time and effort making it
hard for you to look away. Mastodon lets you go about your day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s important to remember that if you are not paying for a service, you are not the customer.
You don&#39;t pay Facebook, advertisers pay Facebook. Advertisers are Facebook&#39;s real customers.
You are the &lt;em&gt;product&lt;/em&gt;
that Facebook is selling to advertisers. (Or, more specifically, your attention span is.) And the more you
stare at Facebook, the more product Facebook can offer to those who want to buy your attention span.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Profit driven social media sites have been making tweaks for years to harvest your attention span,
and some of these tweaks have had surprising effects. A major realization
they&#39;ve had in the last few years is that, if you only want to make your users stare at the screen longer,
the users don&#39;t necessarily have to like what they are seeing. In fact, outrageous content can make
people even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; likely to keep using social media. Twitter doesn&#39;t care if you are using Twitter
because you feel informed by what you are reading or if you feel infuriated by it. Either way, you are on Twitter looking
at ads. Plus, the outrageous content makes you even more likely to post something yourself, since you need
to tell that other person that they are an idiot. So not only does social media show you an endless stream of
content, but it actually skews towards content that makes you angry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is often said that if a company wants your business, they will improve the quality of their service
for their customers. But remember, you are not the customer of social media, you are the product. These companies have massively
increased their revenue by creating the most infuriating, frustrating product that they can.
They aren&#39;t catering to you, they are selling your attention span
to others. Making you mad is great for business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When considering whether some service should be provided by a for-profit business, many
people will ask, &amp;quot;Who cares if someone is making money off of it?&amp;quot; -- suggesting that making money itself
is the ethical issue, and they aren&#39;t bothered by it. A better question is, &amp;quot;If they are making money off of this, what
will they be incentivized to do to make more money?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may sound dramatic, but opting out of profit-driven social media feels like an act
of self respect. I decide that my attention span is for me to use on my own interests, not
to be pushed and pulled by the interests of a Fortune 500 company. If you like the idea of taking your attention
span off of someone else&#39;s shelves, there are a few places to sign up for an account. There&#39;s a
list of them at &lt;a href=&quot;https://joinmastodon.org/servers&quot;&gt;joinmastodon.org/servers&lt;/a&gt;. If you don&#39;t have
a particular niche you&#39;re looking for, you can just pick any general purpose server there.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
